Guide to the A. B. Chapman Music and Drawings
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
A. B. Chapman music and drawings
1874-1897
GEN MSS 957
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.83
(6 boxes) + 1 roll
Autograph manuscript music, including symphonies and hymns, scores; arrangements of hymns and other choral music, scores and parts; a passion-play, score, with watercolor drawings of curtain and stage designs; and notebooks containing music drafts and related notes about music and Christianity. An oversize rolled sheet contains unidentified ink and watercolor drawings.
Chapman, A. B. (Aaron Bennet)
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
6 (Roll) (drawings): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of A. B. Chapman, 1898.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Music, 1874-1897. II. Drawings, undated.
A. B. (Aaron Bennet) Chapman
A. B. (Aaron Bennet) Chapman attended Yale College, leaving in 1871, his junior year, due to health problems. He lived in New Haven, Connecticut, during the 1860s-1890s.
Scope and Contents
Autograph manuscript music, including symphonies and hymns, scores; arrangements of hymns and other choral music, scores and parts; a passion-play, score, with watercolor drawings of curtain and stage designs; and notebooks containing music sketches and related notes about music and Christianity. An oversize rolled sheet contains unidentified ink and watercolor drawings.
Artists -- Connecticut -- New Haven; Choruses, Sacred -- Scores; Composers -- Connecticut -- New Haven; Hymns -- Scores; Passion-plays; Symphonies -- Scores; New Haven (Conn.) -- Religion; Drawings (visual works) -- Connecticut -- New Haven -- 19th century; Watercolors (paintings) -- Connecticut -- New Haven -- 19th century; Artists -- Connecticut -- New Haven -- 19th century; Composers -- Connecticut -- New Haven -- 19th century; Chapman, A. B. (Aaron Bennet)
- Music, 1874-1897, undated; Series I; 0.75; (5 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Notebooks containing sketches are arranged chronologically, followed by music arranged alphabetically by title or type of composition.
  Scope and Contents
  Sketches are in short score; other music is in full score unless otherwise indicated.
  - Notebook, 1874 (Box 1)
    Includes sketches for Symphony no. 1
  - Notebook, undated (Box 1)
    Includes sketches for Symphony no. 3
  - Notebook, undated (Box 1)
    Includes sketches for Symphony no. 7 and Symphony no. 8
  - Notebook, 1879-1880 (Box 1)
    Accompanied by hymns, 1880-1888
  - Notebook, 1881 (Box 1)
    Accompanied by unidentified music and notes, 1881-1884, undated
  - Notebook, 1887 (Box 1)
    Includes a silhouette portrait of Chapman
  - Notebook, 1888-1889 (Box 1)
    Includes sketches for Symphony no. 12
  - Notebook, undated (Box 1)
  - Unidentified music and notes, 1874-1897, undated (Box 1)
  - Choral music, arranged, undated (Box 2 (Oversize))
    Parts for SATB
    Contains: Franz Otto, "A Night in March" and music by Ludwig van Beethoven, Felix Mendelssohn-Bartholdy, and Richard Wagner
  - Hymns, 1879-1880, undated (Box 2 (Oversize))
    Also includes music of other composers, arranged, score and alto part; and printed hymns by an unidentified composer
  - Orchestral music, arranged, undated (Box 2 (Oversize))
    Contains: Giuseppe Verdi, "Miserere" from Il Trovatore, arranged by an unidentified composer, score and incomplete parts; and parts for unidentified music
  - "Sacred Music Drama or Passion Play for Church or Stage", 1889 (Box 2 (Oversize))
    For organ or piano, solo voices, and chorus
    With watercolor illustrations of stage curtains and stage settings
  - Symphony no. 1, 1874 February 5 (Box 3 (Oversize))
    "Begun February 5, 1874; reviewed the fifth time, August 26, 1885"
    "33 Bowdoin St., Boston"
  - Symphony no. 2, undated (Box 3 (Oversize))
  - Symphony no. 3, 1874 May (Box 3 (Oversize))
    "Finished May, 1874, 33 Bowdoin St., Boston, Mass.; final correction, February, 1890, New Haven, Conn."
  - Symphony no. 4, 1874 August 19 (Box 3 (Oversize))
  - Symphony no. 5, "L'Amerique", 1874 October 16 (Box 4 (Oversize))
  - Symphony no. 6, 1874 December 14 (Box 4 (Oversize))
  - Symphony no. 7, 1875 March 17 (Box 4 (Oversize))
  - Symphony no. 8, 1875 July 21 (Box 5 (Oversize))
  - Symphony no. 9, 1875 December 1 (Box 5 (Oversize))
    "Reviewed August 26, 1885"
  - Symphony no. 10, 1876 December 27 (Box 5 (Oversize))
  - Symphony no. 11, 1874 December 18-1880 October 11 (Box 5 (Oversize))
    "Orange, Ct."
- Drawings, undated; Series II; (1 roll)
  Related Archival Materials note
  See also: Music/"Sacred Music Drama or Passion Play for Church or Stage"
  - Unidentified drawings, ink and watercolor, undated (Box 6 (Roll))
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Unidentified drawings, ink and watercolor, undated (Box 7 (Oversize))